Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is ס"ח, Samech-Chet, סנהדרין
Sanhedrin 68, and we will be finishing the פרק perek ארבע מיתות
Arba Mitot and beginning בן סורר ומורה. Ben Sorer u-Moreh. And we
pick up with the last three lines, אמר רבי עקיבא. Amar Rabbi
Akiva. Really says nothing, it's just quoting from the משנה mishnah where
Rabbi Akiva talked about the איסור issur of כישוף, kishuf, of witchcraft,
where Rabbi Akiva says sometimes somebody can do it and be חייב,
chayav, and sometimes פטור, patur, and you make it look like you're
picking a whole field of vegetables and if you really did it
then you're חייב chayav for כישוף, kishuf, and if it was just
illusion, then you are exempt from the איסור issur of חיוב סקילה.
chiyuv sekila. Should mention that the גמרא Gemara earlier in dealing with
the איסור issur of כישוף, kishuf, a few דפים dafim before, said
that the איסור, issur, at least according to one interpretation, of doing
something that looks even as an illusion that you are doing some
type of witchcraft or magic, could be an איסור issur of לא
תעוננו. Lo Te'onenu. Different understandings of exactly what לא תעוננו Lo Te'onenu
is prohibiting. Interesting question of how does it apply nowadays when people
are aware that you're not really doing it, but some illusionists are
very good, so who knows? Anyway, that is a question about whether
there is at least
an איסור דאורייתא issur d'ora'ita without it being a חיוב מיתה. chiyuv
misa.
Anyway, we pick up here, top of now ס"ח עמוד א, Samech-Chet
Amud Aleph, and the גמרא Gemara says the following. אמר רבי עקיבא
מרבי יהושע גמר לה? Amar Rabbi Akiva me-Rabbi Yehoshua Gemar lei? Did
Rabbi Akiva really learn this from Rabbi Yehoshua? Because in the משנה,
mishnah, Rabbi Akiva quotes Rabbi Yehoshua. והתניא, Ve-ha tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, brayta, that it actually seems that he learned this idea
from Rabbi Eliezer, his רבי. rebbe. Let's take a look. Rabbi Akiva
learned both from
Rabbi
Eliezer and Rabbi Yehoshua. כשחלה Kesheh-chalah Rabbi Eliezer, famous story about the
death of Rabbi Eliezer. And just to give you the context, Rabbi
Eliezer was the one of the famous story of the תנורו של
עכנאי, Tanur shel Achnai, where all the חכמים chachamim said that the
oven in a certain case would be טמא, tamei, and Rabbi Eliezer
said טהור, tahor, and they voted against him, and he caused the
walls of the בית מדרש Beit Midrash to bend in and the
river to run backwards, and even a heavenly voice to come out
that he was right, and nevertheless the rabbis replied לא בשמים היא,
Lo Bashamayim Hi, G-d, keep out of it, and the majority has
ruled otherwise. And because Rabbi Eliezer refused to accept the tradition of
the majority rule, he was put into a חרם. cherem. And they
were not, the other rabbis were not able to enter into his
space and to learn with him and speak with him. So now
he is about to die, so let's take a look at this
story. כשחלה Kesheh-chalah Rabbi Eliezer, when Rabbi Eliezer got sick, נכנסו רבי
עקיבא וחבריו לבקרו, nichnesu Rabbi Akiva ve-chaverav le-vakro, so Rabbi Akiva and
his colleagues came to visit him. הוא יושב בקינוף שלו והן יושבין
בטרקלין שלו. Hu yoshev be-kinof shelo ve-hen yoshevim be-traqlin shelo.
He was sitting under his like canopy bed, and they were sitting
in an outer chamber of his room, of his house. ואותו היום
ערב שבת היה, Ve-oto hayom erev Shabbat haya, it was Friday that
day. ונכנס הורקנוס בנו לחלוץ תפילין, Ve-nichnas Hurcanus beno lachlot tfillin, and
Hurcanus his son came to take off his תפילין, tfillin, because you
don't wear תפילין tfillin on שבת. Shabbat. גער בו, Ge'aro bo, and
Rabbi Eliezer yelled at his son, ויצא בנזיפה, ve-yatza bi-nezifa, and he
left the room like being rejected. אמר להן לחבריו, Amar lahen lachaverav,
so he said to, Hurcanus said to the colleagues here, כמדומה אני
שדעתו של אבא נטרפה, ki-midumani she-da'ato shel Abba nitrepa, it seems that
my father's mind is no longer of right mind, that he might
be dying at any moment, because he didn't want me to take
off his תפילין, tfillin, you know, maybe it's an issue of dementia,
and he doesn't realize that it's about to be שבת Shabbos and
you have to take off תפילין. tfillin. אמר
להן, Amar lahen, so Rabbi Eliezer who had overheard this said, דעתו,
da'ato,
and they've took of the side the word
מיושבת, miyushevet, no, his actual דעת da'at meaning my דעת da'at is
totally fine, I am totally of right mind, ודעת אמו נטרפה, ve-da'at
imo nitrepa, or some have דעתו ודעת אמו נטרפה, da'ato ve-da'at imo
nitrepa, meaning you my son and your mother who maybe sent you
to do this, you're the ones that have the problem. היאך מניחין
איסור סקילה ועוסקין באיסור שבות? Heich manichin issur sekila ve-oseqin be-issur shevut?
How is it that it's about to be שבת Shabbos and you're
not concerned about doing things that are could be a מלאכה, melacha,
and here you're worried about me wearing תפילין tfillin which is a
דרבנן? d'rabbanan? Now what did he mean? Means that because it's before
שבת Shabbos is when you have to light candles. Well, right now
we light candles, you know, of course sort of ritualized it, but
in the גמרא, Gemara, the idea of lighting candles right before שבת
Shabbos is just to make sure there's lights on in the house
before שבת, Shabbos, and you have to take care to make sure
you're doing it with a good amount of time, and here he's
saying, look, it's about to be שבת Shabbos and you're so worried
about me taking off your תפילין, tfillin, you should be worried about
making sure that all the candles are lit. So clear, you're the
ones that got the problem, not me. כיון שראו חכמים שדעתו
מיושבת, Ke-van she-ra'u chachamim she-da'ato miyushevet, so oh, one other thing to
point out, what does he mean איסור שבות? issur shevut? You know,
you don't wear תפילין... tfillin... on שבת, Shabbos, that's because שבת Shabbos
is not זמן תפילין. zman tefillin. What איסור שבות issur shevus is
a specific איסור דרבנן issur d'rabonon relating to שבת. Shabbos. So the
idea is that
because you don't wear תפילין tefillin on
שבת, Shabbos, even in the house there's an איסור דרבנן issur d'rabonon
of going outdoors with it because you go out into a רשות
הרבים reshus harabbim and even if you were to do that that
would only be דרבנן d'rabonon because even though שבת Shabbos is not
זמן תפילין, zman tefillin, nevertheless you're still wearing it like a מלבוש,
malbush, like a type of clothing. So that's why worse that could
come from me having my תפילין tefillin on is some איסור דרבנן
issur d'rabonon about שבת, Shabbos, you've got your priorities wrong. So that's
what Rabbi Akiva and all of the colleagues overheard this. כיון שראו
חכמים שדעתו מיושבת עליו, keivan sherau chachamim shedaato meyusheves alav, so the
rabbis saw okay, he is of right mind and maybe also saw
he's still his old sort of feisty self, נכנסו וישבו לפניו מרחוק
ארבע
אמות. nichnesu veyashvu lefanav merichok arba amos. So they entered in to
actually now be in his presence, but they stayed four אמות amos
away because he was in נידוי nidduy and they were not allowed
to enter in to his four אמות. amos. אמר להו, amar lehau,
למה באתם? lamma battem? So he said to them, why have you
come? אמרו לו, amru lo, ללמוד תורה באנו, lilmod Torah banu, we
came to learn Torah from you. אמר להם, amar lahem, ועד עכשיו
למה לא באתם? ve'ad achshav lamma lo battem? And why have you
not come until now? I mean obviously everybody knew the reason because
he was in
נידוי. nidduy. אמרו לו, amru lo, לא היה לנו פנאי, lo hayya
lanu penai, we didn't have enough time, we didn't have free time,
we didn't have the opportunity. So nobody wants to exactly say what
the real reason is. Obviously he's offended that they put him into
נידוי nidduy and as a result he's been excommunicated, he's been kept
at a distance, and they don't want to he's started sort of
expressing his disfavor of course with all of this and they're not
going to explicitly bring it up again. So they're all sort of
dancing around this. Okay. אמר להם, amar lahem, תמיה אני אם ימותו
מיתת עצמן. tammei ani im yamusu misas atzman. So he said I
would be astounded
if you would die like a natural death. That's a pretty harsh
thing to say and of course we know Rabbi Akiva and it
was a time of martyrdom that what happened to Rabbi Akiva and
many of the other rabbis of that time. So here it seems
to be saying look at you have treated me in this way,
here I'm dying, at least he's dying a natural death, let's see
what happens to you. So pretty very harsh feelings are going on
right here.
So אמר לו amar lo Rabbi Akiva, Rabbi Akiva
said שלי מהו? sheli mahu? What is my story in terms of
dying a natural death or not? אמר לו, amar lo, שלך קשה
משלהן. shelcha kasha mishel-lahen. You
it's even going to be worse than them. Your death will even
be worse than theirs and of course we know about the horrific
death of Rabbi Akiva.
So and Rashi says why is Rabbi Akiva's worse because as we'll
see in a minute Rabbi Akiva had the greatest opportunity to learn
from Rabbi Eliezer so he felt that you have lost the most
from this state of not being able to be my student and
my being in נידוי. nidduy. Wow. So okay very heavy. So נטל
שתי זרועותיו, natal shtei zero'osav, at that moment Rabbi Eliezer took his
two arms, והניח על לבו, vehiniach al libbo, and put them on
his heart. אמר, amar, אוי לכם שתי זרועותי, oy lachem shtei zero'osai,
woe to you my two arms, שהן כשתי ספרי תורה שנגללו, shehen
kishtei sifrei Torah shenniglellu, that they're like two ספרי תורה sifrei Torah
that are rolled up. הרבה תורה למדתי והרבה תורה לימדתי. harbe Torah
lamadeti veharbe Torah limmadeti. I've learned so much Torah and I've taught
so much. הרבה תורה למדתי ולא חסרתי מרבותי אפילו ככלב המלקק מן
הים. harbe Torah lamadeti velo chasarti merabbosai afilu kechelev hammelakkeik min hayyam.
I learned so much Torah and I did not take away from
the vast amount of knowledge that my rabbeim had and the Torah
that I've learned, not even as much as a dog would take
that would be lapping up some water from the sea. It's a
little strange image because why do you think that when you learn
Torah from somebody you're taking it away?
It's clear more that what the point is, not just that he
did not make them lose any of their Torah, but that the
amount of Torah that he received even with all the vast amount
of Torah he
learned was like as we would say a drop in the bucket.
There would have been not even as much as a dog would
take by lapping up water from the sea.
והרבה תורה לימדתי, veharbe Torah limmadeti, and I've taught so much Torah,
ולא חסרוני תלמידי אלא כמכחול בשפורפרת. velo chissaruni talmidai ella kemikchol beshapheress.
And my students did not take away from me not even as
much or no more than an eyelash applicator in a tube. So
also only a tiny bit. Now again the idea ולא חסרוני, velo
chissaruni, they didn't take away from me as if the teaching of
Torah makes you lose it, I don't know maybe the sense is
that when you're teaching it you don't have time to do your
own learning, but it's hard to exactly understand that point, but the
bigger point here is what they took from me was also a
drop in the bucket. Now it is interesting that the amount of
you know of makeup or whatever you take when you have an
eyelash applicator and you, in the tube, you're taking a lot more
than a dog that's lapping up from the sea. So it seems
that when he's talking about himself, he can be
very self-negating and say, first of all, the whole image of being
like a dog, but anyway, speak about like, I only took from
my rabbis a tiniest bit, like a dog lapping from the sea.
For his students, he's not going to make such a harsh statement.
He's saying it about them; they're not saying it about themselves. Anyway,
the point is that I had so much תורה Torah to give
and only a tiny bit have I managed to give over. Okay,
ולא עוד v'lo od and now he's going to spell it out.
אלא שאני שונה שלוש מאות הלכות בבהרת עזה. Ela she-ani shoneh shlosh
meiot halachot b'baheret azah. I have three hundred הלכות halachot to teach
about this bright spot of leprosy, בבהרת עזה, b'baheret azah, ולא היה
אדם ששאלני בהן דבר מעולם. v'lo haya adam she-she'alani bahen davar me'olam.
I have all this brilliant תורה, Torah, I have a million details
to teach about this, and nobody ever asked me about them. Now
this idea that nobody ever asked me is very much in fitting
with the image about the
rolled-up ספר תורה, sefer Torah, his two arms being like the, because
an arm is, if you imagine it, it's a closed and sealed,
if it were a scroll,
then the arm is sort of its shaped like a scroll, but
you can't open it and I have all this knowledge, but nobody
is opening me up. It's like a rolled-up ספר תורה. sefer Torah.
And that's the problem. Nobody wants to, nobody has access to all
of this knowledge that I have available. ולא עוד אלא שאני שונה
בשלוש מאות הלכות,
V'lo od ela she-ani
shoneh b'shlosh meiot halachot,
not only about regarding this leprosy spot, this צרעת tzara'at spot, but
I teach three hundred הלכות, halachot, ואמרי לה שלשת אלפים הלכות, v'amri
lei shloshet alafim halachot, some say three thousand הלכות, halachot, בנטיעת קישואין
b'netiat kishuin about planting of vegetables. ולא היה אדם ששאלני V'lo haya
adam she-she'alani or gourds or whatever קישואין. kishuin. ולא היה אדם ששאלני
בהן דבר מעולם חוץ מעקיבא בן יוסף. V'lo haya adam she-she'alani bahen
davar me'olam chutz me-Akiva ben Yosef. Finally the only person who ever
asked me anything about this, about the planting of gourds, it was
עקיבא, Akiva, רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. פעם אחת אני והוא היינו מהלכין
היינו בדרך.
Pam achat ani v'hu
hayinu mehalechin hayinu baderech. Once we were going on the way. אמר
לי רבי למדני בנטיעת קישואין. Amar li, Rabbi, lamdeni b'netiat kishuin.
He said to me, רבי, Rabbi, למדני lamdeni teach me something about
this what you know relating to the planting of vegetables. אמרתי דבר
אחד בנטיעת קישואין. Amarti davar echad b'netiat kishuin.
It almost sounds like he was sort of asking it to him
because to give, to give רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer some opportunity to
teach these הלכות halachot that nobody else had asked for. Not exactly
clear from the context that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva really needed to
know these הלכות. halachot. למדני, Lamdeni, teach me something of what you
know from these הלכות. halachot. Finally, somebody's asking him of some of
his knowledge.
So אמרתי דבר אחד ונתמלא כל השדה קישואין. amarti davar echad v'nitmalleh
kol hasadeh kishuin. I said one thing, and now we're back to
finally our משנה, Mishnah, presumably some type of magical word, and the
whole field filled with these קישואין, kishuin, cucumbers. ואמר לי רבי למדני
נטיעתן,
V'amar li, Rabbi,
lamdeni netiatan, you've taught me how to get them planted, ולמדני עקירתן,
v'lamdeni akiratan, tell me, show me the כישוף, kishuf, the magic that
will get them to be uprooted. אמרתי דבר אחד ונתקבצו כולם למקום
אחד. Amarti davar echad v'nitkappetzu kulla l'makom echad. I said another magical
word, and they all gathered. Now of course the problem here is,
is that how is he able to do this? What, isn't there
like the איסור issur דאורייתא d'Oraita that you're חייב סקילה chayav sekilah
for? So it's in here in the educational context and we'll see,
but still this is going to be a real big question. Of
course the other interesting thing is, as opposed to the idea of
three hundred הלכות halachot by the spot of צרעת, tzara'at, there there's
really questions about the actual הלכה, halachah, what exactly is, would make
it טמא, tamei, what would make it טהור. tahor. This does not
seem to be so much about הלכה halachah per se, you're teaching
like some magic details about כישוף kishuf to which הלכה halachah says
you're חייב מיתה, chayav mitah, but is it really, is this really
like sort of necessary to know in terms of what the exact
הלכות halachot are? Not clear. And that's sort of seems to be
part of the tragedy here. Not only the tragedy that רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer is in נידוי niddui and his students have been separated
from him, but also that
he has all of this knowledge, but it's just like a lot,
a lot, a lot of data. How much relevance is
it and how much does he really have to teach the students
in terms of what they need to learn or in terms to
empower them? See, it's important to remember that the
משנה Mishnah in פרקי אבות Pirkei Avot about the about the שבח
של חכמים, shevach of hachamim, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is compared to
a בור סוד שאינו מאבד טיפה, bor sud she-eino m'abed tipah, like
a cistern that is plastered over that doesn't lose a drop. So
the whole idea of course of a cistern is it has no
fresh water. It's again the water metaphor. It has all the water
that was put in it. It's not losing a drop, but it's
also not producing anything. And that's contrasted to the one who is
מעיין המתגבר, ma'ayan hamisgaber, which is the wellspring that is constantly, you
know, producing more and and and is flowing with water. Very different
image for Rebbi Eliezer here is, you know, he has all of
this תורה, Torah, but the question is is it really very static
or not? It also fits again with the what we know of
Rebbi Eliezer that the גמרא Gemara says, you know, in סוכה Sukka
and elsewhere that he said I've never taught anything that I didn't
learn from my teachers. And he, so he really believed in a
type of a תורה שבעל פה Torah shebe'al peh that was much
more about receiving and passing on. I mean you see this from
the images he used: a ספר תורה, sefer Torah, like, you know,
the water taken from the ocean, giving over the water. So for
him it is really just receiving the traditions and passing them on,
not the human creativity, and that of course explains also what was
going on in the תנור של עכנאי tanur shel achnai story where
he knew that he had his tradition, it was true, doesn't matter
if the majority rule against him. He can't buy into the idea
of לא בשמים היא, lo bashamayim hi, you know, that speaks about
rabbinic creativity and empowerment and he just believes in the passing down
of tradition. So that is him here bemoaning all of what he,
all the knowledge he had that he was not able to pass
down. Okay, אמרו לו, amru lo, so now the sages said to
him, they switched the topic, you know, maybe because they switched it
specifically because he was saying nobody's ever asked me about all the
תורה Torah I have to teach. They now want to check in
with him about his תורה, Torah, ask him about some of the
תורה Torah he has to teach, but they ask a little more
practical. הכדור והאמום והקמיע, Hakadur veha'amos vehakamia, if you have different types
of leather objects that are filled and they're made to be filled
and the filling is to stay there. Because the general principle is
that a כלי, kli, a leather vessel, is only can become טמא
tamei if it is has a בית קיבול, beit kibul, you know,
has something that can be a receptacle.
So like a leather sack would be a perfect example. But what
if it's a type of a ball, you know, like a soccer
ball
that's
made out of leather and that's packed tightly with stuffing, but it's
not made for it to ever come out? So it had a
receptacle, it was the hollow soccer ball, and it was filled, but
it was filled to be one unit. So what's the הלכה halacha
there? Rebbi Eliezer said that it was טמא tamei and the חכמים
Chachamim said that it was טהור. tahor. So they wanted to ask
him, you know, are you still of the same opinion here? So
הכדור, hakadur, which is basically like a soccer ball, והאמום, veha'amos, which
is a, which is a type of a, of like a shoehorn
or a, a flange I think it's called, whatever it is, anyway
that's used for making a shoe on it, also type a piece
of leather that's filled with stuffing, וצרור מרגליות utzror margaliot and a
type of a little bundle that's used like a little pouch that's
used to put in some type of jewels, רש"י Rashi says it
would be like a type of a, like a charm in order
to prevent illness, so you would never take the jewels out.
והקמיע, v'hakamia, I skipped on והקמיע, v'hakamia, so קמיע kamia is a
קמיע kamia is a whatever it's called a type of a charm,
ומשקולת קטנה umishkolet ktana and a ומשקולת קטנה mishkolet ktana and a
small weight that's also covered with leather and maybe not made to
be taken out. So מהו, mahu, what's the story? אמר להן הן
טמאים, Amar lahen hen tme'im, I am still of my position that
they can become טמאים, tme'im, וטהרתן
במה שהן.
vetaharatan
b'mashehen. But at the same time it, they can also become טהור
tahor even with their stuffing in them. The stuffing is not considered
a חציצה. chatzitza. So if you put the whole leather ball into
the מקוה mikva and it became טמא, tamei, you don't have to
take the stuffing out, which is convenient, that would be really hard
if you would. It's a little seems ironic because since the reason
it's considered a receptacle is because it's containing stuffing, you would think
that that would mean you have to conceptualize the stuffing as being
distinct from the ball. And nevertheless the stuffing is not a חציצה.
chatzitza. Okay, that's what he says. Now מנעל שעל גבי האמום min'al
she'al gabei ha'amos מהו? mahu? What if the you have, this is
a different הלכה, halacha, if you have a shoe that is on
this, you know, horn that's being used to be constructed by the
shoemaker and it's totally finished, but it hasn't yet been removed. Is
that yet considered that it's now, is that considered that it's done
and it's a כלי kli and it can become טמא? tamei? Or
until it's removed, even though anybody could just remove it, but maybe
until it's removed it doesn't have the status? So that also was
a debate of him and the חכמים Chachamim and they wanted to
know if he still held by his position. Rebbi Eliezer continues to
hold by all of his positions, he is very rigid, very much
exactly everything that he has taught he keeps on teaching.
So מהו? mahu? אמר להן הוא טהור. Amar lahen hu tahor. That
it would be טהור, tahor, and what, and how does it end?
As he said the word טהור, tahor, יצאה נשמתו בטהרה. yatza nishmato
b'tahara. His soul departed in purity. Now which is obviously saying that
he suffered, you know he died there a death, and you know
that was an elegant of whatever you could say, you know, a
smooth death, but also as he was saying the word טהור, tahor,
so to very fitting type of an end which is interesting because
you know going back to the תנור של עכנאי Tannur shel Achnai
was exactly the same, they were all saying טמא tamei and he
was saying טהור. tahor. So he lived, I guess you could say,
you know, he died as he lived. Very very consistent with all
of his positions and but it was a pure type of a
life. All right, so יצאה נשמתו בטהרה, yatza nishmato betahara, very powerful
whole passage here. עמד רבי יהושע על רגליו Amad Rabbi Yehoshua al
raglav ואמר הותר הנדר. ve’amar hutar haneder. Rabbi Yehoshua then got up
and said the הנדר haneder is now undone, the putting him in
נידוי niduy or excommunication is done. He is dead. Of course now
he is dead but there's rules that still apply if somebody's in
excommunication even after his death and he said now that he's dead
it is over. הותר הנדר. Hutar haneder.
למוצאי שבת פגע בו רבי עקיבא מן קיסרי ללוד. Lemotzaei Shabbos paga
bo Rabbi Akiva min Keisari l'Lod. On מוצאי שבת motzaei Shabbos Rabbi
Akiva
encountered the funeral sort of procession going from קיסרי Keisari to
לוד, Lod, which is interesting because Rabbi Eliezer is from לוד, Lod,
but seems that they were in קיסרי. Keisari. Anyway so they were
taking him maybe to לוד Lod to be buried. היה מכה בבשרו
עד שדמו שותת לארץ. Haya makeh bivesaro ad shedamo shotet l'aretz. And
Rabbi Akiva was pounding on his flesh in such grief until his
blood was pouring on the ground until תוספות Tosafot questioned whatever happened
to the דאורייתא de’oraita prohibition of ושרט לנפש לא תתנו בבשרכם, veseret
lenefesh lo titnu bivesarchem, you know, על מת. al meit. So, but
it seems here it was not intentionally making an incision, but he
was in grief pounding himself until he was bleeding. פתח עליו בשורה.
Patach alav beshura. He opened up in a type of a eulogy
when they were in a שורה. shura. For us, you know, שורה
shura often means standing in the lines as the mourners pass through
and you say המקום ינחם אתכם, Hamakom yenachem etchem, but here it
is a type of a שורה shura where they are standing, you
know, in the middle of the procession and they're eulogizing. ואמר ve’amar
he said, quoting from what Elisha said when Eliyahu departed, אבי אבי
רכב ישראל ופרשיו, Avi avi rechev yisrael ufarashav, my father, my father,
the chariot of Israel and its horsemen.
הרבה מעות יש לי ואין לי שולחני להרצותן. Harbeh ma’ot yesh li
ve’ein li shulchani lehartasotam. I have so much money and I have
no money changer in order to, you know, change my coins. I
have nobody to help me clarify the all of the teachings that
I have. And again this sort again is a, you know, Rabbi
Akiva was the exact opposite of Rabbi Eliezer. He was all about
the human creativity. So here when he so,
you know, so here was Rabbi Akiva representing a totally different type
of approach to תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be'al peh and the what
he was losing from, you know, a money changer does not really
create anything new. I mean it takes your money and it changes
it into gives you smaller coins, makes it maybe more usable, test
on like in the old days where question was whether it was
like, you know, whether the metal was actually the precious metal, whether
it was good quality coinage, tells you if it's good quality or
not. So again very fitting image here of what how Rabbi Akiva
described what it meant to lose Rabbi Eliezer. Anyway after this entire
totally powerful story,
so much so multi-layered, the point of the גמרא Gemara quoting it
here is to say אלמא מרבי אליעזר גמרה. alma me-Rabbi Eliezer gamra.
He learned the prin he learned this whole thing about the about,
you know, picking
קישואין. kishu’in. Apparently it's a zucchini. Anyway and, you know, through כישוף,
kishuf, he learned it from Rabbi Eliezer not from Rabbi Yehoshua. So
the גמרא Gemara says גמרה מרבי אליעזר. gamra me-Rabbi Eliezer. It's true
he learned it from Rabbi Eliezer ולא סברה. v'lo savra. And he
didn't but he didn't really totally understand it. הדר גמרה מרבי יהושע
ואסברה ניהליה. Hadar gamra me-Rabbi Yehoshua ve’asbera nihalei. And then he learned
it from Rabbi Yehoshua and Rabbi Yehoshua explained it to him, which
is again so perfectly apt given the exact description of Rabbi Eliezer.
Okay anyway, היכי עבדי הכי? Heichi avdi hachi? Now finally the גמרא
Gemara ends by saying and how could Rabbi Eliezer have done this?
ואנן תנן עושה מעשה חייב. ve’anan tenan oseh ma’aseh chayav. That if
you actually do it for real and not just as an illusion,
and it sounds like this it was done for real, you actually
are
חייב. chayav. ושאני. v'shani. It's different when you're doing it to understand,
educational purposes, not really for the sake of preparing doing, you know,
doing כישוף kishuf itself, which is quite shocking. דאמר מר לא תלמד
לעשות. de-amar mar lo tilmad la’asot. You should not learn to do
like the abominations of the of the nations, okay, לעשות אי אתה
למד. la’asot iy ata lamed.
You're not allowed to learn to do, אבל אתה למד להבין ולהורות.
aval ata lamed lehavin ulehorot. You can learn for the purpose of
understanding and teaching. Of course it's one thing to learn, it's another
thing to actually do. So it's pretty shocking here that you can
actually do this act of כישוף kishuf because it was for educational
purposes. הדרן עלך ארבע מיתות Hadran alach Arba Misos and with that
we finish ארבע מיתות Arba Misos which really it says ארבע מיתות
Arba Misos but as we've seen the entire פרק perek is about
things that you're חייב סקילה chayav skila for and we're not done
and that continues now as we begin the next פרק perek on
the top of ס''ח ע''ב samach ches amud bais of בן סורר
ומורה ben sorer umoreh which is another case of חייב סקילה chayav
skila but different from all of these other you know this is
really goes in much much greater depth of בן סורר ומורה ben
sorer umoreh than it pretty much goes by most of the others
which is itself fascinating presumably apparently that is a way of an
expression of the principle that בן סורר ומורה ben sorer umoreh never
happened and the reason the תורה Torah gave it was דרוש וקבל
שכר drush v'kabel sechar you know that you should learn it and
receive reward for the explicating maybe that has something to do with
why the משניות Mishnayos and the גמרא Gemara go into so much
detail with בן סורר ומורה ben sorer umoreh let's take a look.
בן סורר ומורה Ben sorer umoreh אימתי נעשה בן סורר ומורה eimasai
na'aseh ben sorer umoreh so בן סורר ומורה ben sorer umoreh is
one who gets סקילה skila so that's and when does a
person child or whatever young man become a בן סורר ומורה ben
sorer umoreh rebellious and wayward child? משיביא שתי שערות Mi-she'yavi shtei se'aros
from the time he brings two pubic hairs and he's 13 so
he הלכתית hilchatit is an adult ועד שיקיף זקן v'ad sheyakif zakan
until his beard fills out. התחתון
ולא העליון Ha-tachton v'lo ha-elyon it refers to his lower beard not
his upper beard meaning his pubic hair אלא שדיברו חכמים בלשון נקייה
ella shedibru chachamim bilshon nekiya but the Rabbis spoke in euphemism so
they called it a beard שנאמר כי יהיה לאיש בן shene'emar ki
yihyeh l'ish ben and how do we know this is the age
when somebody can become a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer umoreh because
it says when a man has a son בן ולא בת ben
v'lo bas so son and not daughter בן ולא איש ben v'lo
ish a son and not a full man so it's only at
a very narrow stage when he is still obligated in מצוות mitzvos
but not yet a fully grown man and so why not just
say it means that he's actually a minor? So the משנה Mishnah
ends by saying קטן פטור שלא בא לכלל מצוות katan patur shelo
ba l'chlal mitzvos but it can't be a minor because a minor
isn't obligated so because he's described as because he has to be
an adult he has to have brought two pubic hairs but because
he still has to be a בן ben it's not limited until
he becomes at least you know this his sort of sexual characteristics
have filled out at that stage he is no longer in the
בן ben category he's already a full איש. ish. So let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. קטן מנלן דפטור Katan minalan d'patur
how do we know a minor is exempt? So the גמרא Gemara
says מנלן minalan what do you mean how do we know? כי
קתני טעמא ki katani ta'ama it says right there in the in
the משנה Mishnah the reason שלא בא לכלל מצוות shelo ba l'chlal
mitzvos he's not yet obligated in מצוות mitzvos וכי תימא היכא אשכחן
דענש הכתוב דהכא איצטריך קרא למפטריה
v'chi teima heicha ashken d'anash hachasuv
d'hacha itzterich k'ra l'miftarei and also when you say how do we
know he's exempt means you're starting besides it's already been said in
the משנה Mishnah but the very question of how do we know
he's exempt meaning it means that your default assumption is that he
should be liable. Where do we ever find that the תורה Torah
has a minor who's liable that you should start by asking how
do we know the minor is exempt? So the גמרא Gemara says
אנן הכי קאמרינן anan hachi ka'amrinan no here's what we want to
say אטו בן סורר ומורה אחטאו נהרג atu ben sorer umoreh achatei
neherag what do you think that the בן סורר ומורה ben sorer
umoreh is being killed for his for his sin? How what kind
of sin is it you know to get drunk to eat to
eat meat okay disobey your parents that's a sin worthy of death?
No על שם סופו נהרג al shem sofo neherag he's being executed
because the תורה Torah looks into his future and sees that he's
on a path that he will ultimately the way we'll see later
in the גמרא Gemara the גמרא Gemara will say it you know
sees that he'll eventually become a bandit and kill people and therefore
the תורה Torah says let him die when he's innocent not let
him not die after he becomes guilty. That obviously is a very
shocking idea which has to deal with why the גמרא Gemara says
that it never happened okay but the principle here is I should
actually pause here it's important to say right at the beginning of
this פרק perek the point that רמב''ן Ramban says. רמב''ן Ramban says
that in this section of the תורה Torah you know sort of
the שופטים Shoftim section there are a number of מצוות mitzvos where
the תורה Torah says after somebody's put to death it says וכל
ישראל ישמעו ויראו v'chol Yisrael yishme'u v'yira'u all the people will hear
and will be afraid and that teaches you that part of the
point of the death penalty here is not necessarily that the sin
is so grievous but that it is important for broader societal purposes
for people to understand you know to protect various institutions. So for
example for example one of those places is where you know זקן
ממרא Zaken Mamre the elder of the court who teaches against the
teaching of the סנהדרין Sanhedrin if you have to try to you
know you have to make sure that you are protecting the institution
of the authority of the court so there is going to be
a very harsh punishment for somebody who acts in a way that
could undermine in the broader society their understanding about you know their
awe and their sense of the authority of the of the court.
So here too with this understanding it's like you know this. Maybe
what he did is not so bad, but how could this
threaten the parental authority? That's the way רמב"ן Ramban understands וכל ישראל
ישמעו ויראו. v'chol Yisrael yishme'u v'yira'u. So that's at least look, not
saying that that fits with our sort of sensibilities or how we
might think of things, but and you know is the sort of
authority of parental authority so threatened that this is what it needs?
Maybe. But anyway, but that at least is a way of saying,
you know, not killed for the sake of his sin. Okay? I'm
not exactly על שם סופו al shem sofo either for broader societal
purposes. But anyway, the בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer u'Moreh is not
killed because the sin itself is what is so grievous. And if
that's true, then maybe he doesn't even have to be an adult.
If the whole if the whole punishment is out of proportion, then
it's not really about the sin, maybe he doesn't even have to
be an adult. דכיון דעל שם סופו נהרג, de'kivan de-al shem sofo
ne'erag, since he's being killed for, you know, the future and not
how he's acting now, אפילו קטן נמי, afilu katan nami, maybe even
a minor. ועוד, Ve-od, that's so number one, that's why our starting
assumption was a minor should be liable. And also, בן ולא איש,
ben velo ish, so קטן משמע. katan mashma. So when the גמרא
Gemara says, you know, it should be a בן ben and not
a man, and that's how it learned not a full man and
you know his pubic hair did not fully fall out. But really,
בן ולא איש ben velo ish suggests not a man at all,
a minor. So the פסוק pasuk actually both logic and the פסוק
pasuk would point us to a minor. So how do you know
that he has to be technically an adult? אמר רב יהודה אמר
רב דאמר קרא, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav de'amar kra, because the
פסוק pasuk says כי יהיה לאיש בן, ki yihiyeh le'ish ben, because
it says when a man has a son who is סורר ומורה,
sorer u'moreh, so the juxtaposition of those two words לאיש בן, le'ish
ben, בן הסמוך לגבורתו של איש, ben hasamuch ligvurato shel ish, it
means a son who is close,
it means a son that is close to the you know to
the vigor of a man. So somebody who is not yet fully
a man, but is but is already technically a man. רש"י Rashi
sort of suggests that you that the point is to read it
in reverse, like כי יהיה לאיש בן, ki yihiyeh le'ish ben, it's
כי יהיה בן לאיש, ki yihiyeh ben le'ish, when the son just
becomes a man, okay that's when he is חייב chayav but not
when he is a fully a man and yet biologically, halachically he
is a man already. Okay, עד שיקיף זקן התחתון ולא העליון, ad
sheyakif zakkan hatachton velo ha'elyon, until the beard fills out, the lower
one not the upper one. תני רבי חייא, Tani Rabbi Chiya, עד
שיקיף עטרה, ad sheyakif atara, so רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya he he
the way he taught this was not the he didn't use the
phrase of the beard but the crown. Okay, כי אתא, ki ata,
now crown sometimes is what's used to refer to the tip of
the penis as well but obviously that's not exactly where the hair
is growing in, but another way of euphemism of referring to this.
כי אתא רב דימי אמר, ki ata Rav Dimi amar, when רב
דימי Rav Dimi came he said, הקפת גיד ולא הקפת ביצים, hakafas
gid velo hakafas beitzim, we're talking about the hair that is around
the actual shaft of the penis not about not around the testicles.
אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, קטן שהוליד אין בנו נעשה בן
סורר ומורה. katan sheholid ein beno na'aseh ben sorer u'moreh. Now a
different point. If the minor actually has a child, so he's at
this young age of 13 and a few months or whatever, and
he has managed to impregnate somebody and the person has given birth,
maybe another sign again of his wayward ways. Anyway, once he is
a father he is no longer in the category of בן ben
even if he is of the right age. קטן שהוליד אין בנו
נעשה בן סורר ומורה
katan sheholid ein beno na'aseh
ben sorer u'moreh שנאמר shene'emar oh I'm sorry hold on. Oh excuse
me I got that wrong. Actually it's not talking about whether he
can become a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u'moreh but whether his
son can become a בן סורר ומורה. ben sorer u'moreh. So somebody
who was a minor when he actually fathered a child, okay that
person that person's son cannot become a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer
u'moreh or that person who he fathered, the child who he fathered
when he himself was a minor, that child cannot be a בן
סורר ומורה. ben sorer u'moreh. How do you know that? Because the
פסוק pasuk says כי יהיה לאיש בן, ki yihiyeh le'ish ben, when
a man has a son, לאיש בן ולא לבן בן, le'ish ben
velo le'ben ben, when a man has a son but not when
a child has a son. So the son of somebody who is
a who himself was who fathered him when he himself was a
child, that son cannot become a בן סורר ומורה. ben sorer u'moreh.
So the גמרא Gemara says how how can you learn from that?
האי מיבעי ליה לרב יהודה אמר רב, Hai mibaye lei le'Rav Yehuda
amar Rav, don't you need this for what רב יהודה אמר רב
Rav Yehuda amar Rav teaches? That the idea about that you know
we're talking about somebody that has just become a man? That's the
juxtaposition of לאיש בן, le'ish ben, just become a man, not to
teach you a man has a son and not a son has
a son? אם כן לימא קרא im ken leima kra כי יהיה
בן לאיש. ki yihiyeh ben le'ish. No, because then it could have
said it in the reverse order. Which is same thing, when a
man has a son, but saying the word בן ben first. כי
יהיה בן לאיש, ki yihiyeh ben le'ish, when a child is had
by a man, and that would have suggested exactly the דרשה drasha
בן לאיש, ben le'ish, a child that is just about. The fact
that it said בן לאיש, ben l'ish, if it had said, you
know, a son is to a man, it would have been exactly
the teaching of בן לאיש, ben l'ish, a somebody who has just
become a man.
The fact that it reversed it and said לאיש בן, l'ish ben,
כי יהיה לאיש בן, ki yihyeh l'ish ben, so שמע מינה, shma
mina, so the fact that it chose to do it that way
is telling you both. שמע מינה לרב חסדא, shma mina l'Rav Chisda,
telling you like Rav Chisda, only when a man has a son,
not when a child has a son, not when a minor has
a son, that son would not count. So the גמרא Gemara says
ואימא כולה להכי הוא דאתא, ve-eima kula l'hachi hu d'ata, so maybe
it's just telling you that teaching of Rav Chisda, only when a
man has a son and not telling you the idea that when
the boy has just reached manhood. אם כן נימא קרא בן איש,
im ken nima kra ben ish, then it wouldn't have had the
ל. lamed. This is גמרא Gemara always trying to figure it exactly
articulated it this way to allow us to learn all the things.
So what if it had said, you know, when there is a
son of a man, which would have suggested a son of a
man and not the son of a son, son of a child.
מה לאיש בן, ma l'ish ben, the fact that it had the
ל lamed and said it this way, שמע מינה תרתי, shma mina
tarti, that allows us to learn out both things. Fine, that's the
principle that that only when that not only is it a somebody
who has just reached manhood but also only the son of a
man, not the son of a child. Now this idea, says the
גמרא, Gemara, basically suggests, not suggest, you know, more or less implicitly
states that that somebody who is a boy who is under age,
under thirteen, can father a child. So is this really true? גמרא'ס
Gemara's not going to ask that empirically, it's going to ask based
on other texts. So the גמרא Gemara says ופליגא דרבא, u-pliga d'Rava,
this argues on Rava, דאמר רבא, d'amar Rava, Rava says קטן אינו
מוליד, katan eino molid, a minor boy cannot father a child, שנאמר,
she-ne'emar, as we know from the פסוק, pasuk, ואין לאיש גואל, ve-ein
l'ish go'el, if this man has no redeemer. This is talking about
somebody who stole money or denied the money, took an oath, and
then he admits that he's lying and he has to return it
to the person. But the תורה Torah says if this person has
no redeemer, if the person is dead and there's nobody who is
his heir for whom the person who swore falsely could redeem the
money to could return the money to, he has to go ahead
and bring it to the כהן kohen and bring a special קרבן
korban and so on. That's called גזל הגר gezel ha-ger because as
the גמרא Gemara is going to say, the only person who this
could be referred to who has nobody who is related to him,
what Jew has nobody that another Jew that's related to him unless
this person is a גר, ger, a convert. So וכי יש לך
אדם בישראל שאין לו גואל? ve-chi yesh lecha adam b'yisrael she-ein lo
go'el? Is there any person in the Jewish people that has no
redeemer, meaning that has no relative?
אלא בגזל הגר הכתוב מדבר, ela bi-gezel ha-ger ha-katuv medaber, it must
be talking about when it was stolen from a convert. Okay, top
of ס"ט עמוד א', Samech Tet amud Aleph, דאמר רחמנא, d'amar rachmana,
and the תורה Torah says איש, ish, that if וכי אין לאיש
גואל, ve-chi ein l'ish go'el, so now we're talking about a גר,
ger, and if now and if this גר ger has no redeemer,
why? Because a גר ger could have a redeemer. Who could be
his heir? Who could be if he had a child. All right,
but if you know that he doesn't have a child, then the
money goes to the כהן. kohen. איש אתה צריך לחזור עליו אם
יש לו גואלים אם לאו, ish ata tzarich lachzor alav im yesh
lo goalim im lav, so it says if this man has no
child, then you go ahead and give it to the כהן. kohen.
קטן, katan, but if he was a minor, אי אתה צריך לחזור
עליו, i ata tzarich lachzor alav, you then you wouldn't even have
to find out if he had an heir, you wouldn't have to
do any investigation. Why? בידוע שאין לו גואלים, be-yadu'a she-ein lo goalim,
because you would know that he has no redeemer because obviously if
he were under age he could not have fathered a child. So
based on this דרשה drasha here is the learning out from this
פסוק, pasuk, okay, Rava's learning out from this פסוק pasuk the principle
that we assume that a minor has not fathered a child or
minor is not able to father a child and therefore you only
have to worry if this person has an heir if he was
already a man. So גמרא Gemara setting this up as a debate
whether a minor can father a child and we will see tomorrow
how this continues to play out.